Finding aid for Hinsdale family papers, 1857-1963
Bentley Historical Library
Hinsdale family papers
1857-1963
Bentley Historical Library
Hinsdale family.
851586 Aa 2
2 linear feet
Family of Burke A. Hinsdale, professor of education at the University of Michigan and president of Hiram College. The collection contains the papers of Burke Hinsdale and the papers of his three daughters, Mary Louise, Ellen Clarinda, and Mildred. Materials include correspondence, diaries, and photographs.
The collection was donated by Mildred Hinsdale (donor nos. 1055 and 1427 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Burke Aaron Hinsdale was professor of the Science and the Art of Teaching at the University of Michigan from 1888 to his death in 1900. Hinsdale received his A.M. from Williams College in 1871 and his Ph.D. from Ohio State University in 1888. Hinsdale was President of Hiram College from 1870 to 1882 and superintendent of the Cleveland public schools from 1882 to 1886.
Hinsdale's three daughters were also educators. Mary Louise Hinsdale, also referred to as Mary Louisa, (1866-1946) received her doctorate from the University of Michigan in 1912. She also studied at Radcliffe College, where she worked on a book, A History of the President's Cabinet. Mary taught political science and history at Grand Rapids Junior College, in addition to serving as a teacher and an educational administrator in Indiana, Ohio, and Michigan. Ellen Clarinda Hinsdale (1864-1958) received her Ph.D. from Göttingen University in Germany in 1897 and wrote a book titled, The First American Students in Germany. Ellen worked as a teacher of Germanic languages and literature at Mt. Holyoke College from 1897-1931. Mildred Hinsdale (1871-1971) graduated from the University of Michigan in 1895 and became a teacher of history and political science in Detroit and Grand Rapids. She later taught at Grand Rapids Junior College where she founded the Grand Rapids Alumnae Club.
The Hinsdale family papers consist of material from Burke A. Hinsdale and his three daughters Mary, Ellen, and Mildred. The collection contains correspondence, journals, photographs, and other materials documenting the personal and professional lives of the Hinsdale family.
Some of the correspondents represented in the collection include Randolph G. Adams, John R. Alden, James B. Angell, Denis W. Brogan, Nicholas M. Butler, Donald J. Cawling, William E. Dodd, Lucretia Rudolph Garfield, Benjamin Harrison, Albert B. Hart, Anne O'Hare McCormick, Alice Freeman Palmer, Theodore Roosevelt, Henry Stimson, and Charles Sumner.
Arranged in 5 series: 1. Burke A. Hinsdale. 2. Mary L. Hinsdale. 3. Ellen C. Hinsdale. 4. Mildred Hinsdale. 5. Photographs.
Business records.; Europe -- Description and travel.; Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946.; Voyages and travels.; Travelers -- Europe.; Women -- Michigan -- Grand Rapids.; Women college students -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Women travelers -- Europe.; Children.; Diaries.; Oral histories.; Photographs.; Women's resources.; University of Michigan. Class of 1895.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1891-1900.; Hinsdale, B. A. (Burke Aaron), 1837-1900.; Hinsdale, Ellen Clarinda, 1864-1958.; Hinsdale, Mary L.; Hinsdale, Mary Turner.; Hinsdale, Mildred, 1871-1971.; Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951.; Alden, John Richard, 1908-1991.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Brogan, D. W. (Denis William), 1900-1974.; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947.; Cawling, Donald J.; Dodd, William Edward, 1869-1940.; Garfield, James A. (James Abram), 1831-1881.; Garfield, Lucretia Rudolph, 1832-1918.; Harrison, Benjamin, 1833-1901.; Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1854-1943.; Hinsdale, Albert, 1809-1882.; Hinsdale, B. A. (Burke Aaron), 1837-1900.; Hinsdale, Ellen Clarinda, 1864-1958.; Hinsdale, Mary L.; Hinsdale, Mildred, 1871-1971.; McCormick, Anne O'Hare.; Palmer, Alice Freeman, 1855-1902.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950.; Sumner, Charles, 1811-1874.
- Burke A. Hinsdale, 1857-1900; 1.3 linear feet
  The papers of Burke A. Hinsdale include correspondence dealing with family affairs, business and professional activities, and European travels. Much of his correspondence is typescript and photographic copies of letters exchanged with James A. Garfield.
  - Correspondence
    (most of the correspondence in the period 1857-1881 is with James A. Garfield who preceded Hinsdale as President of Hiram College; these letters are either typescript or photographic copies)
    - 1857 (Box 1)
    - 1858 (Box 1)
    - 1859 (Box 1)
    - 1860 (Box 1)
    - 1861 (Box 1)
    - 1862-1863 (Box 1)
    - 1864-1865 (Box 1)
    - 1866 (Box 1)
    - 1867 (Box 1)
    - 1868-1869 (Box 1)
    - 1870 (Box 1)
    - 1871, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1872, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1873 (Box 1)
    - 1874, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1875, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1876, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1877 (Box 1)
    - 1878-1879 (Box 1)
    - 1880-1881 (Box 1)
    - 1882-1890 (Box 1)
    - 1891-1892 (Box 1)
    - 1893-1896 (Box 1)
    - 1897-1900 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Data Forms on University of Michigan Faculty Members
    - A (Box 1)
    - B (Box 1)
    - C (Box 1)
    - D (Box 1)
    - E-F (Box 1)
    - G (Box 1)
    - H (Box 1)
    - J-L (Box 1)
    - M-N (Box 1)
    - P-R (Box 1)
    - S (Box 1)
    - T-V (Box 1)
    - W-Z (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 1)
  - Copy of Garfield-Hinsdale letters; correspondence between James Abram Garfield and Burke Aaron Hinsdale; edited by Mary L. Hinsdale ( 1949 ) (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook of articles written during European Tour (Box 2)
- Mary L. Hinsdale, 1891-1946; 0.3 linear feet
  The Mary L. Hinsdale series consists of the personal papers of Mary, as well as her professional endeavors. While some of the correspondence to and from Mary covers personal relationships, most of these letters are regarding her writings in politics and history. The largest portion of the series consists of journals documenting Mary's trips to Europe, primarily through Germany and Italy. The series also includes notes from an interview between Mary and Lucretia Garfield, wife of President James A. Garfield.
  - Correspondence, 1901-1946; 2 folders (Box 2)
    (includes a letter of Theodore Roosevelt, 1911)
  - Reviews of Garfield-Hinsdale letters (Box 2)
  - Interview with Mrs. James A. Garfield (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Diaries of European Trips and student notebook at Radcliffe, 1891-1900; 9 volumes (Box 2)
- Ellen C. Hinsdale, 1887-1956; 0.2 linear feet
  The Ellen C. Hinsdale series contains material from her travels as well as her studies. A number of travel journals are included in the series, documenting trips across Europe as well as the rest of the world. The series also contains material from her time at Göttingen University, both about her time as a student during the 1890s, and also the renewal of her Ph.D. in 1956. The rest of the series consists of personal correspondence from her father, and also some from friends.
  - Correspondence, 1887-1900 (Box 2)
  - Papers concerning studies at Göttingen University, 1895-1897 (Box 2)
  - Journals
    - European Trip, 1888 (Box 2)
    - Trip around the world, 1928-1929; 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous travels, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Papers concerning ceremony at University of Göttingen, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Mildred Hinsdale, 1876-1963; 0.2 linear feet
  The Mildred Hill series contains a journal from a trip to Europe, as well as personal correspondence from friends, as well as some professional about her publications. One item of note from the series of transcriptions of interviews with Mildred where she talks about her time as a University of Michigan student and later as the creator of the Grand Rapids Alumnae Club.
  - Correspondence
    - 1876, 1897 (Box 2)
    - 1933-1936 (Box 2)
    - 1937 (Box 2)
    - 1938-1959 (Box 2)
  - Journal of trip to Russia, 1928 (Box 2)
  - Transcriptions of oral interviews, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
    (concerning student life at the University of Michigan in the 1890s and the founding of the Grand Rapids Alumnae Club)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 2)
- Photographs, 1885-1895; undated; 0.1 linear feet
  The Photographs series primarily consists of portraits of Burke A. Hinsdale, his wife Mary Turner Hinsdale, and their children Ellen Clarinda, Mary Louise, and Mildred.
  - Burke Aaron Hinsdale Portraits
    - Originals, undated; 1 envelopes (Box 2)
    - Copies and Reproductions, undated; 1 envelopes (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Hinsdale Family Portraits, 1885-1895; 1 envelopes (Box 2)